14.2, respect.
You will find this in Chapter 3 of the
Code of Ethics and Professional Conduct.
Respect.
Section 1, description of respect.
Respect is our duty to
show a high regard for
ourselves, others, and the
resources entrusted to us.
Resources entrusted to us may include
people, money, reputation, the safety of
others, and natural or environmental
resources.
An environment of respect engender's
trust, confidence and performance
excellence by fostering mutual
cooperation, an environment where diverse
perspectives and views are encouraged and
valued.
Did you notice that it said respect is our
duty to show a high regard for ourselves?
What does that mean?
Shouldn't we be showing a high regard for
others?
Yes, but it's one of those tricky things
to explain.
But think of it this way, if we show a
high regard for ourselves, respect
ourselves, then we will never
do anything to harm ourselves
or do anything that makes
others think less of us.
Now you may have seen adverts on TV
warning us not to get drunk.
In Australia we had a
series of advertisements
and they were titled Respect Yourself.
It showed people getting drunk and falling
over and looking volition, starting fights
with the friends, if you really respect
yourself, you're not going to lie or cheat
or steal because these will make you look
bad to others.
Always do the right thing even when nobody
is looking and you can always hold your
head high and because you're acting honestly
and fairly you are respecting others.
Section 2, respect aspirational standards.
As practitioners in the global project
management community, one, we inform
ourselves as about the norms
and customs of others and avoid
engaging in behaviours they
might consider disrespectful.
2.
We listen to others' points of view,
seeking to understand them.
Three, we approach directly those persons
with whom we have a
conflict or disagreement.
And when it says we approach them
directly, I take that demean rather than
going to other people in bad
mouth on the person, we go to
that person directly so we can
try to sort it out one and one.
Number four, we conduct
yourselves in a professional
manner even when it is not reciprocated.
Not reciprocated means you're doing the
right thing, you're being professional,
they are not being professional to you.
You would still remain professional.
Comment.
An application of these provisions is that
we avoid engaging in gossip and avoid
making negative remarks to undermine
another person's reputation.
We also have a duty
under this code to confront
others who engage in
these types of behaviours.
Most of this is obvious, but the last
aspirational standard is a difficult one
because it calls upon us to stand up for
others who are being disrespected.
And you would notice it said, we conduct
ourselves in professional manner,
even if it's not reciprocated.
But as I said, that means
you act professionally
even when they don't act professionally.
However, I think it goes a bit further
than that.
I think this doesn't mean that you should
let others be disrespectful to you.
It means that you don't argue or fight
with them.
You remain dignified.
You remain professional.
You remain polite.
And you report their behavior to the
appropriate authority.
Number three, respect mandatory standards.
So these are the ones with the aspirational
standards, as I mentioned earlier.
It doesn't mean that they aren't any way
optional that you could leave them out.
You have to do your absolute best to
attain the aspirational standards.
If you fail at an aspirational standard,
it doesn't mean you're unethical.
It just means you've got some work to do.
However, if you feel a mandatory standard,
you are being.
on ethical.
So number three, respect mandatory
standards.
As practitioners in the global project
management community, we require the
following of ourselves and other
practitioners.
One, we negotiate in good faith.
What does good faith mean?
This means that we do not mislead someone.
And if it's obvious that they have
misunderstood something and it seems to be
working in our benefit
that we should clarify it
rather than taking
advantage of the the situation.
Number two, we do not exercise the power
of our expertise or position to influence
the decision or actions of others in order
to benefit personally at their expense.
Three, we do not act in an abusive manner
towards other people.
Four, we respect the property rights of
others.
And property rights of others,
that would include, don't play judge your
eyes because somebody owns a rights to
that work.
And it brings us to the end of respect.
The next lesson is 14.3 fairness.
Please read the corresponding
section in the Code of
Ethics and Professional
Conduct before watching the video.